<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Droidalone | My little Android warehouse]]></title>
  <link href="http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/categories/droidalone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fedepaol.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-12T22:13:01+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://fedepaol.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Federico Paolinelli]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DroidAlone - Reloaded]]></title>
    <link href="http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/2012/11/25/droidalone-reloaded/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/2012/11/25/droidalone-reloaded</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Whenever I speak with another android developer, the occasional chat goes to &#8220;what did you develop?&#8221; question.<br />Last time it happened at droidcon uk, and for the first time I felt something wasn&#8217;t completely right when I showed my DroidAlone app.<br /><br />DroidAlone is a useful app (so they say) that comes into play whenever you forget your phone at home. With a simple sms protected by a password choosen by the user, it can be activated. From that moment, it will start notifying you of any missed calls and sms. It also ships a lot of other nice features, such as phone location retrieval and auto reply via sms (if you want to inform the caller that he can reach you to another number).<br />The full description of DroidAlone can be found at&nbsp;<a href="http://www.fedepaolapps.com/app/droidalone/">Missed Calls for Android</a>&nbsp;.<br /><br />Everything seems to work well, it has a lot of good reviews and the few users are happy.<br />Except one thing. It looks (looked) like this:<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.fedepaolapps.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/main_screen1.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="320" src="http://www.fedepaolapps.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/main_screen1.jpg" width="213" /></a></div><a href="http://www.blogger.com/"></a><span id="goog_1451563458"></span><span id="goog_1451563459"></span><br />It also had another view with the list of events. The other developer&#8217;s reaction was &#8220;ugh&#8221;. And then I realized that I can&#8217;t keep producing new stuff ignoring what I have around, especially if this is the case of the only app I manage to sell a bit.<br /><br />So, when I got home I decided to change the ui &#8220;just to make it more pleasant&#8221;. &nbsp;Then I opened the code, and I realized that my two year&#8217;s old code needed a bit more than a refresh.<br /><br />Here what was wrong:<br /><br /><ul><li>it used tabactivity, which is very old fashioned. I decided to add the actionbar.</li><li>from the event list view, you had to click on the item to see the details of the event. The details where shown into a dialog. Ugh (again). In the new version I wanted all the details to be visible since they are not so long.</li><li>All the properties of the views in the layouts where explicit. No styles anywhere. The color resources where &#8220;background_color&#8221;, or &#8220;title_color&#8221; instead of some name that remind you the color. I had to put a heavy hand on that.</li><li>I tried to use gridlayout a lot since it seem to be the more efficient way to dispose a layout.</li><li>There was no empty list information.</li><li>A lot of calls where deprecated. I switched to the most modern versions.</li><li>All the data was contained in a sqllite storage without using a content provider. I switched to using a content provider and a cursorloader, which ended up in a more compact code. I didn&#8217;t need anymore to use a broadcast to notify the ui that the data was changed.</li><li>DroidAlone uses broadcast receivers to be notified of incoming calls / sms. Even tough the sms receiver must be enabled because an activation sms can be received at anytime, the call receiver is needed only when the app is active. I then used the package manager to disable it when not needed.</li><li>I wanted to refactor a lot of code. A lot of brackets where on the new line instead of the same line of the method (a la C), and it bothered me a lot. I also trusted lint and changed a lot here and there.&nbsp;</li></ul><div><br /></div><div>Other than these things, I redraw (by my self) a lot of the assets using inkscape. Because I soon got bored to export the resources in 4 different resolutions folders, I wrote a simple python script to do that for me. You can find it <a href="https://gist.github.com/4127778">here</a>&nbsp;.</div><div><br /></div><div>More than that, I got REALLY REALLY bored while writing the content provider, so I ended up writing another python script to automatically generate the content provider for me, as described in my previous <a href="http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/2012/11/11/android-content-providers-generator">post</a>. You can find the <a href="https://github.com/fedepaol/Android-sql-lite-helper">android content provider generator here</a>.&nbsp;</div><div><br /></div><div>Finally, I switched the project to maven because I am getting used to that solution, especially in case I want to add robolectric tests and keep working with intellij.</div><div><br /></div><div>The new version of the app hasn&#8217;t been released yet (I want to have it running for a while on my phone before releasing it, just to be sure that I didn&#8217;t break anything).</div><div><br /></div><div>This is how the new version will look like&nbsp;</div><div><br /></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-KFbMTLsxs5w/ULKCXaGOnLI/AAAAAAAAJS4/CVeElRWX6wA/s1600/screen3.tiff" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="320" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-KFbMTLsxs5w/ULKCXaGOnLI/AAAAAAAAJS4/CVeElRWX6wA/s320/screen3.tiff" width="194" /></a></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">So, this is how a &#8220;little ui polishing&#8221; ended lasting more than two weeks (of my spare time). I am also glad that I think my old code is not that good. I like to think that I am better than two years ago.</div><div><br /></div><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div><br /></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DroidAlone - Opensourced]]></title>
    <link href="http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/2010/12/27/droidalone-opensourced/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/2010/12/27/droidalone-opensourced</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I released DroidAlone on the market in the early summer. You can find a description at the following url&nbsp;<a href="http://sites.google.com/site/droidalone/">DroidAlone - Missed call for Android</a><br />It is a paid app, and it costs something like 0.99 euros. It has been downloaded something like 150 times since then.<br /><br />I also had some issues in choosing its name: at first it was homealone, but I was afraid to Mr Culkin knokin&#8217; to my door for royalties, then it was phonealone but there was already one, and then it moved to DroidAlone. So what I suggest you is to look for your name after you choose it: you won&#8217;t have to change everything just only because you discover too late that somebody else chose the name before.<br /><br />However, today I decided to release its source files on https://github.com/fedepaol/DroidAlone/<br /><br />Why did I choose to do that? After all I spent some time working on it, and I think it&#8217;s a quite nice application.<br /><br />Well, first of all, I must be honest. The money I am getting from it is not that much, and I don&#8217;t think releasing the sources will affect my sells in a negative way. Even if it gets more popular, it would be quite hard to stop piracy. Finally, this is not my primary job, so I don&#8217;t depend on it for living.<br /><br /><br />Apart from this, there are other reasons. One of them is that the only code I wrote and made public is the one from geotagger. It was my first experiment on android and with java as well. I think I got slightly better with droidalone, and I wanted to show it.<br /><br />My android and java skills are still improving, but since I am now working with other people it will be hard to opensource the stuff I am working on now (and please remember I do android only outside my daytime job).<br /><br />So, I really hope it may help somebody, it has some nice stuff in it, like sms and call handling, and mail sending.<br /><br />So, enjoy. I&#8217;d really love to hear feedback..<br /><br />Federico</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
