<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | My little software store]]></title>
  <link href="http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fedepaol.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-26T20:45:18+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://fedepaol.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Federico Paolinelli]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New (Side) Chapter]]></title>
    <link href="http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/2018/10/26/a-new-chapter/"/>
    <updated>2018-10-26T07:33:23+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/2018/10/26/a-new-chapter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>It&rsquo;s been a while</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s more than a year since my last blogpost which incidentally (or not) it happened right a month before the birth of my second child. In the past year I lost a lot of sleep, and now I am kind of getting back to normality (which means new side gigs :-)).</p>

<p>My interests moved from Android and mobile in general to Go and distributed systems, which is what I am probably going to write about in the next blogpost. Still, I am not sure if the green robot will catch my attention again but at the moment I am focusing on Go.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s the reason why I replaced the name of the blog to a more general one.</p>

<h4>A lot of interesting things happened:</h4>

<p><strong>I attended conferences</strong>: I went to QCon London and to Gophercon London.</p>

<p>After the experience of speaking at <a href="http://fedepaol.github.io/blog/2014/02/20/rest-interaction-in-android/">Droidcon Italy 2014</a>, <strong>I re-started speaking in public:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>DevFest Pisa 0.1, where I spoke about transitioning from C to Go <a href="https://talks.godoc.org/github.com/fedepaol/go-for-c-devs-talk/goforcdevs.slide#1">Golang for C developers</a></li>
<li>Local GDG meetup, where I introduced Go and spoke about some concurrency patterns and <a href="https://talks.godoc.org/github.com/fedepaol/howtotrainyourgophers/howtotrainyourgophers.slide#1">How to train your gophers</a></li>
<li>Golab.io, the Italian Go conference, where I spoke about <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/fedepaol/fast-messaging-with-nats-and-go">messaging with nats and go</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The last one was an awesome experience where I had the chance to speak in front of an international audience and meet so many interesting people.</p>

<p><strong>I started contributing to a Go OSS project</strong>, namely <a href="github.com/gomods/athens">Athens</a>, the proxy for Go dependencies. It&rsquo;s nice to have a way to give something back to a thriving community.</p>

<h4>What is coming next</h4>

<p>Blogposts! I will probably write about the same stuff I spoke at golab, and keep blogging about Go and distributed systems.</p>

<p>Keep tuned !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
